Curriculum Vitae

Name R. Hamed MSc.

First Name Raed

Date of Birth 19 September 1992

Nationality Lebanese

Expertise Statistics, Seasonal Forecasting, Crop

yield variability, Water management

Address: Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam- IVM

De Boelelaan 1111, 1081 HV Amsterdam

Netherlands

Telephone +31645968197 Email raed.hamed@vu.nl

Key Qualifications

Raed Hamed is a PhD researcher within the Water & Climate Risk group of the Institute for Environmental Studies (IVM) at Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam. His work focuses on developing storylines that will investigate the impacts of current and future climate variability on staple crop production in key hotspot regions around the world. This will be done using a combination of machine learning and system dynamics modeling. The research is embedded in the RECEIPT project, an EU-funded project on climate risk storylines.

Raed holds two bachelor's degrees in Agribusiness and Agricultural Sciences from the American University of Beirut. He then obtained his MSc in Climate Studies at Wageningen University completing his thesis focused on seasonal streamflow forecasts for South America.

Before starting at the VU Amsterdam, Raed worked for the environmental consultancy company <u>FutureWater</u> on the EU-funded project <u>IMPREX</u> where he analyzed seasonal forecasting skill of hydrological and crop-related variables for a specific region in the South East of Spain.

Educational background

2019 – present PhD student, Department of Water and Climate Risk at the

Institute for Environmental Studies, Vrije Universiteit

Amsterdam.

Thesis: Impacts of current and future climate variability on

global staple crop production: A storyline approach.

Supervisors: Prof. Dr. Jeroen Aerts, Dr. Anne Van Loon, Dr.

Dim Coumou

2016 – 2018 MSc. Climate studies, Wageningen University.

Thesis: Skill analysis of seasonal forecasting of hydrological anomalies. Supervisor: Dr. Ronald Hutjes, Water Systems and Global Change unit.

2011 – 2016 BSc. Agricultural Sciences + Agricultural Engineering Diploma,

American University of Beirut, Lebanon.

2011 – 2014 BSc. Agribusiness, American University of Beirut, Lebanon.

Professional Experience

2018 – 2019 Climate data analyst/Researcher, FutureWater,

Wageningen, the Netherlands.

2015 – 2016 Research assistant, American University of Beirut, Lebanon.



Recent Assignments and projects

2019 – Present PhD student within the agricultural work package of the European

Union-funded (H2020) project RECEIPT(https://climatestorylines.eu/) on developing storylines of climate risk connecting Europe to the

world

2019 – 2019 Application of the Decision Tree Framework in Chancay-

Lambayeque watershed in Peru- Extreme value analysis.

(World Bank study)

2018 – 2019 Researcher within the agriculture-drought work package in European

Union-funded (H2020) project IMPREX(https://www.imprex.eu/) on developing climate services and improving predictions of hydrological

extremes

2018 – 2019 Develop seasonal climate services for Agriculture using the Copernicus

Climate Data Store. (Climate-KIC pathfinder)

Language Skills

Arabic : mother tongue

English : fluent in writing and speech French : fluent in writing and speech

Spanish : moderate

Computer Skills

Programming : R, Python, Bash

Standard software : MS Office